

## ARUN VIJAYAN Rugma, Killy, Kattakada PO, Thriuvananthapuram, Kerala, 695572

+91- 9791135588 +91- 9209009346 arunvijayan2000@gmail.com

#### About Me

A Technical professional with over 28 years of assorted experience in General Administration, Facility Management, Security & Safety assignments across the organisational hierarchy of Indian Air Force as well as Manufacturing Industries. Seeking career where my expertise and skills can be effectively utilized towards betterment of organisation. A veteran Warrant Officer (Junior Commissioned Officer) of India's most disciplined organization – Indian Air Force, retired on 31 May 2016 and presently working as Administration and Security Manager at Everest Industries Ltd responsible for its west and south zone factories.

## Trainings & Certifications

Trained in security and military discipline, installation security, cyber security, information warfare, contingency management and Closed Circuit Camera management.

Undergone Leadership course from Indian Air Force and underwater scuba diving and life-saving /rescue course from the Indian Navy.

Undergone aircrew rescue and disaster management training from the Indian Air Force

Trained in explosive handling techniques, use of various security and communication gadgets including DFMD, HHMD, X-Ray baggage machines, surveillance cameras, fire-fighting equipment and emergency evacuation techniques.

Handled weapons/small arms and regular firing practice with modern weapons like INSAS, LMG, Sten-MC, other rifles, pistols and revolvers

Participated in various disaster management and rescue operation at Chennai and Orissa during natural calamities

Earned President's warrant, various commendations and medals for exceptional and meritorious performance during Defence service career.

Completed 'Basic and Advanced Study in the Field' course conducted by United Nations Department of Safety & Security (UNDSS)

Internal Auditor-ISO/IEC 27001:2013 - Information Security Management Systems (ISMS)

## Work History

Everest Industries - Jan 2022- till date - Admin & Security Management - West and South zones (Maharashtra , Madhya Pradesh, Gujrat & Tamil Nadu Plants)

Bhilosa Industries Pvt Ltd - Jul 2017 - Jan 2022 Asst General Manager- Vigilance & Electronic Security

Indian Air Force : Junior Warrant Officer
May 1994 - May 2016 General Administration

#### Skills & Proficiencies

- General Administration & Facility Management
- Security Management & Loss prevention
- Security Automation
- · Safety Management
- Vigilance & Intelligence
- Access Control & Pass Management
- Admin support during setting up of New Units
- Security Audits, Preparation of SOPs & Investigations
- CCTV Surveillance, Automation, Camera Analytics
- RFID /Barcode based Weighbridges and Systems
- Crisis & Disaster management

## IT Experience

More than 8 years of IT experience software development using Oracle with experience in various phases of software development like planning, requirement analysis, application design & architecture, testing, configuration, deployment, maintenance and control.

Configuration and management of CCTV systems including working knowledge in various VMS software and its analytics

Proficient in MS Office Suite, SAP software and having ample knowledge in Hardware and Networking.

Certified Business Professional Programmer ('O' Level) from DOEACC Society.

Certification from Oracle University in Oracle 10g Application and Developer 2000 from HCL

Certificate Course in Red Hat Enterprises - Linux Networking and Administration

#### Languages Known

English - Read /Write /Speak

Hindi - Read /Write /Speak

Malayalam - Read /Write /Speak

Date Of Birth - 28 Feb 1977 Marital Staus - Married

Tamil - Read /Write /Speak

#### **Educational Background**

Degree in Mechanical Engineering

Technical Diploma - Mechanical

Graduation in Arts (Kanpur University) with first division

Undergraduate in Physics, Chemistry and Mathematics - first division (Kerala University).

#### SECURITY MANAGEMENT ROLES HANDLED

Security access control management of men and material (approx. 4500 personnel and around 350 vehicles per day at site).

Developing and implementing security SOPs, policies, deployment, recruitment & training of security personnel

Planning and execution of security mock drills and other exercises

Participated in Risk Assessment survey and analysis along with several third party teams

Preparation and implementation of SOPs for material movement, access control, weighbridge operations, visitor management, CCTV surveillance ops, deployment & duties of security team etc.

Monitoring and supervision of scrap management /disposal

Information/ reports / returns / Management Information System (MIS).

Looking after the security management of the foreign nationals who visits for projects.

Imparting safety training and road discipline /parking procedures inside company premises to security cadre as well as drivers

Preparation and circulation of case studies and LFI (Learning from the Incidents).

Continuous evaluation of technology needs and its coordination

Operation of 24X7 state of art security control room and its analysis using VMS analytic tools.

Planning, installation, management and updation of CCTV cameras and SAS installed across the site.

Responsible for the overall coordination of the organization's response to a crisis, in an effective, timely manner; planning disaster/emergency management programs.

Collecting, collating & disseminating vigilance information.

Conducting detailed investigation of security breaches for compliance.

Liaising with district & state police authorities, other companies, Govt. Authorities for maintaining cordial relations; coordinating and escorting of key personnel/ VIP's/ VVIPs including Defence Minister and other senior dignitaries.

Security induction program for newly inducted GETs, DETs and security staff and developing, managing and monitoring the performance of multi-skilled work force and conceptualizing needbased training programs for performing security operations.

#### SAFETY ROLES HANDLED

Continuous inspection of project sites, to ensure a hazard-free environment and develop, implement, enforce policies/ guidelines that reduce the risk of accidents/Incidents

Responsible for keeping policies up-to-date, meeting the latest standards, and establishing new policies from time to time as more and newer risks are discovered. Identification of hazards and to establish procedures and policies to overcome such situations.

Active involvement in conduct a safety investigation to determine root causes / what procedures may have gone wrong and to gather necessary evidence to identify the root cause of the accident based on which the findings and recommendations are published to prevent recurrence of such accidents / incidents.

Verification of tools and equipment to ensure good quality and promoting safe practices on site/plant.

Carrying out safety drills / demonstrations / trainings and exercises on managing emergency situations and testing effectiveness of emergency response drills / activities

Responding to workers' health and safety concerns. Arranges OSHA-mandated evaluations / audits of the plant /site. Coordinates all issues regarding hazardous materials or waste. Attending project planning meetings and collaborating with construction managers

Establishing and maintaining health and safety communication and implementation of safety policies across various plants

Continuous monitoring of all safety related documents, reports and issues to keep them updated and managing all relevant communications with government departments in regards of safety

# SECURITY CONTROL ROOM OPERATIONS & SECURITY AUTOMATION

Planning, installation and maintenance of CCTV cameras and SAS system installed across the site.

Ensure timely collection, compilation, and dissemination of information from SCR to relevant officials.

Ensure all required SOPs (routine and emergency operations / functioning) are available in the Security Operation Center and updated up to the last amendments.

Continuously evaluate technology needs and coordinate with Head–Security, Technology / Site management (for budget / operations approval) to deploy the technology.

Ensure end-to-end coordination of Security activities from Security Control Room. Develop and deploy mechanism for managing coordination.

Ensure all time operational availability of Security /IT Applications deployed for managing access system / material management system.

Planning and negotiations with automation vendors for design basis and SLAs.

Continuous monitoring and implementation of latest and user-friendly Security Automation System.

Establishment and operation of 24x7 state of art security control room and MIS generation.

Crisis management

Overall supervision, performance evaluation and skill-development for all Security Technology team

Analyse internal processes and recommend and implement procedural / policy / systems changes to improve overall operations and services provided to the internal customer Training and Development of the officers and control room operators on Security automation.

#### ADMINISTRATIVE ROLES HANDLED

- General Administration
- Facilities Management
- Recruitment & Training
- House Keeping & horticulture Management
- Labour Management and vendor negotiations
- Office Administration
- New project Admin set up & Support
- Canteen Management
- Employee Engagement & Retention management
- Rent agreement and rented accommodation management
- Motivation and counseling
- Govt. Offices Liaison
- Team performance analysis & Assessment
- Employee Welfare
- Documentation & Prioritization of tasks
- Asset management
- Budgeting, cost control & Improvement
- Infrastructure Management
- Handling of sensitive records
- Sourcing & Procurement
- Travel Desk Management
- Clubhouse Management
- Guest house & workers colony management
- Staff quarters management
- Landscaping and green belt development
- Organising ladies club activities, social gatherings & Event Management
- CSR activities